Guide to the IBT Education Department records, 1980-2008 IBT0012
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
IBT Education Department records
unknown
1980-2008
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America
International Brotherhood of Teamsters
IBT0012
3 Linear Feet
The Education Department, later known as the Teaching and Learning Department, develops programs and materials to train Teamster officers, staff, stewards, and members on topics of concern for the Union, including methods for securing better contracts, organizing new members, political action, and all aspects of union administration. The department also serves as advisor to the Teamsters Human Rights Commission, helping to develop programs and materials relevant to human rights issues. The records reflect the department's role in adult and vocational education to help members stay current with job skills.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into one series. Files within the collection are organized alphabetically by title then chronologically within each title.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials relating to the International Brotherhood of Teamsters Training and Development department. The materials include general information for technical training, including adult education presentations and general information, press releases, meetings, quarterly reports of the Skills For Tomorrow program and the School To Work program, and materials from a Teamster Workshop. Computer generated statistics on the inclusion of locals in Teamsters Workshops is also included. The material dates from 1980-2008.
bib
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical / Historical
According to Old1.Teamsters.org, "The Education Department develops programs and materials to train Teamster officers, staff, stewards, and members on topics of concern for the Union. The department works to encourage member involvement in securing better contracts, organizing new members, winning better laws, and strengthening local unions. The Education Department sponsors the Teamsters Leadership Academy, which provides training on all subjects vital to local leaders, bargaining, organizing, political action, and all aspects of union administration. The department also conducts educational programs for joint councils and local unions on the role of the steward, effective bargaining and building membership participation. The department works closely with International Trade Divisions and Trade Conferences to enhance their meetings/conferences. All programs and materials are continually updated to meet the needs of Teamster locals throughout North America. The department serves as advisor to the Teamsters Human Rights Commission to develop programs and materials relevant to human rights issues. The department also provides staffing to support special projects like contract campaigns, and works closely with other IBT departments to better serve the needs of Teamster officers and their members."
Labor unions -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Labor unions; Labor; Adult education; Vocational education
- Worker Training, 1997,2003; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Technical Education in American High School, 4 April 2002; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Teaching Techniques For Labor Education, 2004; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Office of Vocational and Adult Education, 16 January 2002; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Office of Vocational and Adult Education Presentation, 2002; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Skills For Tomorrow - National Advisory Board Member Mailings, 2000-2002; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- School To Work Grant Proposal, June 2001; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Skills For Tomorrow - General Info, 2003; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- School To Work - General Info, 1999-2000; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- SKills For Tomorrow Annual Meeting, 2003; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Teamsters Press Release, 1999; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Teamsters Press Release, 2000; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- School To Work Press Release, 5 October 1999; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- School To Work Press Release, 2001; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Skills For Tomorrow - First Quarter Report, 2000; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Skills For Tomorrow - Second Quarter Report, 2000; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Skills For Tomorrow - Third Quarter Report, 2000; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Skills For Tomorrow - Fourth Quarter Report, 2000; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Skills For Tomorrow - Second Quarter Report, 2001; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Skills For Tomorrow - Third Quarter Report, 2001; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Skills For Tomorrow - Fourth Quarter Report, 2001; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- SKills For Tomorrow - Seventh Quarter Report, 2002; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Skills For Tomorrow - Eight Quarter Report, 2002; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Skills For Tomorrow - Ninth Quarter Report, 2002; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Skills For Tomorrow - Tenth Quarter Report, 2003; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- SKills For Tomorrow - Eleventh Quarter Report, 2003; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Skills For Tomorrow - Twelfth Quarter Report, 2003; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- SKills For Tomorrow - Final Report, 2003-2004; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- School To Work - First Quarter Report, 2000; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- School To Work - Fourth Quarter Report, 2000; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- School To Work - Sixth Quarter Report, 2001; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- School To Work - Second Quarter Report, 2002; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Teamsters Workshop - Instructors and Staff, 1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- A Well Informed Membership is Our Best Security - Legal, 1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- A Well Informed Membership is Our Best Security - Government Relations, 1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- A Well Informed Membership is Our Best Security - Drive, 1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- A Well Informed Membership is Our Best Security - Safety and Health, 1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- A Well Informed Membership is Our Best Security - Research and Education, 1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- A Well Informed Membership is Our Best Security - Communications, 1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- A Well Informed Membership is Our Best Security - Local Union Administration, 1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- A Well Informed Membership is Our Best Security - Out Of Work Benefits, 1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- A Well Informed Membership is Our Best Security - Titan, 1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- A Well Informed Membership is Our Best Security - Organizing, 1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- A Well Informed Membership is Our Best Security - Economics, 1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Teamsters Workshop Computer Printout Analysis, 2 July 1980; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Teamsters Workshop Computer Printout Local Unions That Have Not Attended the Teamster Workshop, 2 July 1980; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Teamsters Workshop Computer Printout All Participants Listed Under Their Respective Joint Councils, 2 July 1980; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Teamsters Workshop Computer Printout All Participants Listed According to Session Attended, 2 July 1980; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Teamsters Workshop Computer Printout Alphabetical Listing of All Participants, 2 July 1980; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Teamsters Workshop Computer Printout All Participants Listed Under Their Respective Conferences, 2 July 1980; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Focus on Union Administration Manual, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Focus on Negotiations Manual, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Focus on Stewards Manual, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Teamsters History Magazine Publication, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Rail Conference Manual, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
- New Members Manual, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Stewards Manual, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
- New Members Manual (Spanish Version), Undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Stewards Manual (Spanish Version), Undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Leadership Seminar Pamphlet, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Teamsters Honor American Veterans Pamphlet, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Who is Really Fixing Our Airplains? Expose, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- IBT RISE Project, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Education Department Brochures and Pamphlets, Undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Strike Benefits Assistance Program Manual, ND; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Retirement and Family Protection Plan, December 31, 1972; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- 'How to Find Information About the Employer', Handbook for Organizing Seminar, January 16, 1984; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Teamsters 1996-1997 Contract Campaign Planner "Countdown to the Contract", Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- 'Reglamento para le elecion de 2000-2001 de los sidicato internacional de la IBT', 'Regulations for the 2000-2001 election of the leaders and delegates of the international union of the IBT', Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Intervention Guide on Unionism Teamsters Canada Education Department, October 2004; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- The Teamsters Directory of International Departments, Trade, Divisions, and Trade Conferences, November 2008; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- American Labor History Told by Those Who Lived It, AFL-CIO Education Department, Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- "Proud to be a Teamster" Lyrics, ND; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Speech for Teamster/Labor History Timeline, ND; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Timeline: The Past 100 Years: Key Events in American Labor History, ND; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- A Short History of American Labor, 1985; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Chicago Federation of Labor Correspondence between Irwin E. Klass and Stuart Kaufman, February 19, 1988; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- 1993 AFL-CIO/UCLEA Conference Worker Education and Literacy Workshop Materials, Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- IBT Education Department Workplace Violence Prevention Training, 1997-1998; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- A Short History of America Labor, 2000; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Events in US Labor History, 2001; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Labor History: Blood and Heritage Program and Notes, August 1, 2001; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Diversity Works, Undated; IBT0012 (Box Shared Box 36, Folder 7)